A Guide to the James Fenton Bryant Papers, 1861-1866
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
James Fenton Bryant Papers, 1861-1866
The Library of Virginia
23546
56 leaves
James Fenton Bryant
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 9 June 1950, from Edgar Jackson, Franklin, Virginia.
Alternative Form Available
Transcripts of letters can be found in Three Rebels Write Home.
Biographical Information
James Fenton Bryant was born 22 February 1841 at "Bloomfield" in Southampton County, Virginia, to James Deberry Bryant and Elizabeth Sugars Bryant. He attended private school in Southampton County, and a preparatory school in Albemarle County. Bryant was attending the University of Virginia when the Civil War began. He returned to Southampton County and joined Company A, 13th Virginia Cavalry. He served for the duration of the war, and was wounded at the battles of Brandy Station and Five Forks. After the war ended, Bryant returned to the University of Virginia to finish his education. He then received his medical degree at New York University. Returning to Southampton County, Bryant began practicing medicine in the town of Franklin. When Franklin was incorporated in 1876, Bryant was elected its first mayor. Bryant also served as Southampton's first superintendent of Schools. Bryant married first Lydia Gabrielle Barrett (1852-1882), and they had at least 4 children. Bryant and his second wife, Maggie G. Bryant (b. 1867) had at least 1 child. James Fenton Bryant died 16 January 1909.
Scope and Content
Letters, 1861-1866, from James Fenton Bryant (1841-1909) of Southampton County, Virginia, to his father, James DeBerry Bryant (1805-1886); his step-mother, Mary Louise Nutt Bryant (1843-1913); and his sister Rosa E. Bryant (1844-1891), all of Southampton County, discussing army life and inquiring after relatives and friends. Bryant discusses camp life, campaigning in northeastern North Carolina during 1862, and fighting in Virginia during 1864. Also included are letters from his sister Rosa and his uncle, William R. Bryant, concerning family and local news. Bryant also received a letter from M. M. Davis and Company of Petersburg, Virginia, containing swatches of cloth for uniforms.
Contents List
- Letter to James DeBerry Bryant, 20 June 1861.
- Letter from Rosa E. Bryant, 23 June 1861.
- Letter to Mary Louise Nutt Bryant ("Cousin Mollie"), 27 June 1861.
- Letter from M. M. Davis and Company, 29 June 1861.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 8 July 1861.
- Letter from William R. Bryant, 16 July 1861.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 22 July 1861.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 8 August 1861.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 17 August 1861.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 4 September 1861.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 14 September 1861.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 3 November 1861.
- Letter to Rosa Bryant, 5 November 1861.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 18 December 1861.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 4 February 1862.
- Letter to Rosa Bryant, 23 March 1862.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 16 April 1862.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 23 April 1862.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 3 May 1862.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 7 May 1862.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 9 December 1862.
- Letter to Mary and Rosa Bryant, 10 January 1864.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 5 June 1864.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 1 November 1864.
- Letter to Rosa Bryant, 5 November 1864.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 12 November 1865.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 18 January 1866.
- Letter to James D. Bryant, 13 June 1866.
- Letter to Mary Bryant, 30 December 1866.